Ryan Rana

Software Developer / Student

2 Kraushe Rd Warren NJ 07059 908-873-4657 ryanrana04@gmail.com https://ryanrana.github.io/index.html https://www.linkedin.com/in/ryan-rana-544b761b3/

SKILLS

I am a student at Watchung Regional Highschool interested in Computer Science and Machine Learning. I am skilled in Python, Front-end Development, HTML, Web Dev, Research, Scientific Writing, JS, PHP, Jupyter, Pandas, Raspberry Pi, NumPy, Back End Development, and Machine Learning Models (Unsupervised and Supervised).

EXPERIENCE

Datanexxt, NYC - Software Intern

May 2022 - PRESENT

 Software Intern working on deploying IT infrastructure with the latest technologies for cost, efficiencies and agility.

Course Turtle, Warren NJ - Founder/Developer

Aug 2021 - PRESENT

 Founder and Programmer of an Internet Startup that allows teachers and students to share their school schedules online within their school community to make it easier for students to network with one another. Developed in HTML and PHP. Hosted with AWS.

Medium - Writer on Various Programming and Al Topics

Jul 2021 - PRESENT

 Writing Articles once a week on various topics within Computer Science including AI, Python, Web Development, and Current Events. They also may include actual project builds, as well. Previous Articles include "Intro to Neural Networks" and "Intro to Computer Vision". All articles include original visuals as well.

Self-employed - Fullstack Freelance Developer

Aug 2019 - PRESENT

 Completed many projects for clients online with the use of various platforms and general contact. Projects included personal websites, company websites, as well as Stock Prediction and Sports Prediction with Machine Learning. I also edited articles for business professionals as well as private programming lessons for people in ages ranging from 9-35.

Bricks 4 Kidz - Part-time Teacher

Jun 2019 - Aug 2019

 Taught and Assistant Taught EV3 Programming, Scratch(Block Programming), and Python to 4th-5th graders during B4K summer camp programs.

EDUCATION

Watchung Hills Regional High School, Warren NJ - Diploma

Sep 2020 - Jun 2024

Activities and societies: TEDxWHRHS (Speaker), Computer Science Club(Vice President), FPSPI (Vice President), FBLA, Economics, Model UN, Student Newspaper(Student Interview and Technologies Writer)

Udacity - NanoDegree

Jan 2021 - PRESENT

Completed Online Courses: Data Structures & Algorithms in Python, Deep Learning, Intro to Artificial Intelligence, Intro to HTML and CSS, Intro to TensorFlow for Deep Learning, Intro to Data Analysis

Volunteering

Stem In Place, NYC - Vice President

Apr 2021 - PRESENT

- 2021: Teaching Volunteer and Course Creator: Created a 5 day Web
 Development Curriculum for Middle Schools, which involves them learning
 HTML, CSS, and JS. It also includes time for them to complete a personal
 project of their own. I also taught the curriculum in online classes with up to
 60 students.
- 2022: Vice President: Recruited and Organized 40+ instructors, Organized all Content, Worked to Schedule and Recruit Members, Changed Website and Logo Layout, Brought team from 20 instructors to 45 and brought signups from 600 to 1500.

HillsHacks, Warren NJ - Organizer

Nov 2021 - PRESENT

• Founder and Programmer of this Internet Startup that allows teachers and students to share their school schedule online within their school community

AWARDS

Qualified for IEEE NJ Young Engineer Award for NJRSF

Mar 2022

 For my Project, "Around-The-Pipe Audio Based Water Tracker for Home Residents"

Qualified for NJIT CPCP Award for NJRSF

Mar 2022

 For my Project, "Around-The-Pipe Audio Based Water Tracker for Home Residents"

Top 30 David Riccardo National Econ Challenge in New Jersey

Mar 2022

• Scored in the Top 30 representing the Economics Club at WHRHS

3rd Place winner in Congressional App Challenge 2021 NJ-07

Dec 2021

 An app that can scan various household items and classify them with Machine Learning, to then produce a pricing estimate for each of those items. The purpose of this app is to make it easy for insurance estimators to create a pricing estimation. Won 3rd Place in 2021 NJ-07 Congressional App Challenge. I had the opprutnity to present the project to representative Tom Malinowski.

First Level Winner of Google Code-in

Jan 2020

 Completed several open-source projects including the intro web page for OpenMRS.

3rd Place at Repl.it Music Program 2019

Mar 2019

 Built an application that allows users to compose music. It won 3rd in a REPL challenge in 2019. The project was called Virtual Note.

Projects

- ARGlasses A consumer app by Jay Fu, Brian Gan, Arjun Singh, and Ryan Rana that uses augmented reaility to allow users to try on different pairs of glasses on their face without ever having to leave their house. Made in a single weekend and submitted to a variety of hackathons.
- Cone A PHP application that allows users to share all their social media, contact information, and external links by QRCode. It has a login/signup page for users to create an account, an automatic QRcode generator, and a sharable link.
- ELO algoritham based NFL predictor An ELO Ranking system uses the ELO ranking system to rank NFL teams using historical data and then predecting output of games.
- Elimination Based Wordle Solver Algoritham A python application that solves actual wordles. Firstly uses words with maximum amount of common letters and then uses response on the guessed word to eliminate specific words that don't satisfy existing conditions and then using the new list to find

which words have the most common letters, this process is repeated over and over again.

- Around-The-Pipe Audio Based Water Tracker for Home Residents This research presents a revolutionary approach that utilizes audio to
 measure the amount of water going through a household pipe at any given
 time with supervised machine learning models.
- CourseTurtle A startup aimed at making an easier way to analyze student and teachers school course shedules. It allows for users to create their own accounts and share the data in a extremley accesible way.
- QuickEstimate An app that can scan various household items and classify
 them with Machine Learning, to then produce a pricing estimate for each of
 those items. The purpose of this app is to make it easy for insurance
 estimators to create a pricing estimation. Won 3rd Place in 2021 NJ-O7
 Congressional App Challenge. I had the opprutnity to present the project to
 representative Tom Malinowski.
- WHRHS New Tab Extension A chrome extension that overides the new tab for WHRHS students chromebooks. It is pre-installed on all 2000+ chromebooks.
- Global Emmison Calculator A HTML site I worked on with Amar Shah and Chris Doss to calculate the carbon emmisons in and near any US Cities.
- Digital Vision Digital Vision is a wearable technology built to assist the
 blind in their routine. Using a Raspberry Pi coded with Python it takes live
 videos from a small camera and uses an object detection module from the
 YOLO package to report objects in front of the user through a pair of iPhone
 earbuds. For those who don't prefer to use the earbuds or are deaf there is
 also a small vibration motor to let the user know if someone is there. The
 project is currently being used by my grandmother in India.
- **The Power of Artificial Intelligence** My first TedX talk on the applications and future of Artificial Intelligence.
- Virtual Note A HTML Website that allows users to compose music in the easiest way possible. Won 3rd place at Repl.IT Competition in 2019.
- Buisness Meeting Summarizer Business Meeting Summarizer to take record meetings as audio, convert to text using NLP, and extractive summary to condense the meeting contents.
- Insem Camera Foot Traffic Counter An ML project that scrapes live cam video addresses from insecam.org(Online Free Public Directory of Security Cames) and counts and detects people in each frame using the YOLO database.
- WHCS Website The official website for the Watchung Hills Regional Highschool Computer Science Club.